# Eric Bidelman

### **Principal Software Engineer · Frontend**

San Francisco, CA ebidel@gmail.com 734.717.9479

<u>ebidel.com</u> · <u>github.com/ebidel</u> · <u>twitter.com/ebidel</u>

### **SUMMARY**

Respected full stack web dev with over 15 years of technical leadership in product development, tooling, and Developer Relations. I enjoy leading teams to build experiences for millions of users, helping standards bodies design new specifications, and collaborating in open source. My passions include UI, design, code quality, performance, accessibility, developer productivity, tooling, and being data driven.

### **EXPERIENCE**

**Lyft** · *Principal Engineer* FEB 2019 - PRESENT (3 yrs) San Francisco, CA

- Founded Web Design Systems team. Led creation, multi-year roadmap, and adoption of two new design systems used by all web teams at Lyft. Collaborated with 12 eng & designers, fostered 50 additional contributors from 12 orgs, oversaw dev of 60 high quality components, upheld company and peers to industry standards (WCAG 2.1 a11y, performance), architected foundational patterns (dark mode, animation, icons) and tech stack (NextJS, Rollup, styled components, tree shaking) used by rest of Frontend.
- Led major product<sup>1</sup> & technical initiatives for several orgs: Growth, Infra, Identity, Integrity, Business, Deliveries, and Rentals teams amounting to \$80M/yr in revenue & cost savings.
- Catalyzed <u>ride.lyft.com</u> PWA from ideation to \$30M/yr product in 12mo. Sold leadership on expanding business to new users. TL for 9 eng, designer, PM, DS which built e2e Rider app, profile, gift cards, Lyft Cash, server driven ui, payment features for desktop/mobile web. Grew to 4.1% of all user signups as a new low friction onboarding funnel.
- Scaled PWA architecture to platform for 7 other Lyft products, reducing tech debut, maintenance, and allowing teams to launch new products in weeks vs. months.
   Proactively influenced 4 orgs to consolidate, mentored 35 peers, aligned architecture, reviewed specs, and ensured code quality across product silos.
- Active in hiring and developing others in eng, design, PM. Founded the Frontend Working Group, Performance Task Force, and FE Mentorship Program, resulting in changes to the career ladder and hiring loops, and pioneering the company's official mentorship program. SWE internship program reviewer, promo coach, URM sponsor, and member of Hiring Committee, hiring over 126 FTEs. Personally mentored 16 ICs, 2 promoted to Staff.
- Promoted to first and only Principal Engineer in Frontend role.

<sup>&</sup>lt;sup>1</sup> See major Lyft launches & projects

MAR 2008 - FEB 2019 (11 yrs)

### Senior Staff Developer Programs Engineer, L6-L7

- Lead on Web Developer Relations for a global team of 32. Oversaw platform launches, influenced direction of major browser APIs and web standards.
- Defined Chrome team's strategy for external devs to be productive & successful on the modern web. Coordinated narrative and integrations with other Google developer teams.
- TL of dozens<sup>2</sup> of developer & product site launches and well-known open source tools used by 80M devs.
- Organized Chrome's presence during large developer events (Google I/O, Google Developer Days, Chrome Dev Summit).
- Well respected IC internally and externally in the web dev community. Interviewed over 150 candidates, growing our global Developer Relations team to 550. Mentored new team members. 5 promotions, 53 spot/peer bonuses, 34k Twitter followers.

### Senior Developer Programs Engineer, L5

- Built and maintained libraries, SDKs, samples, large demo apps, tools, wrote educational content, presented talks to reach devs around the world. My content has been seen 200M+ views.
- Launched <a href="https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https://https:/
- Developed internal analytics dashboards, scripts, and <u>tools</u> for team to understand metrics and impact of our work for leadership.

### **Developer Programs Engineer**

- Authored, maintained, and implemented significant features in numerous client libs for early Google APIs (Drive, Product Search, Health, Sites, Blogger, <u>OAuth</u>) making them available to language devs for the first time (PHP, Ruby, Python, JS, Java, .NET, C++).
- Consulted top tier partners integrating with Google developer products: Amazon, Disney, EA, AOL, MySpace, Yahoo, Dropbox, Box, ING, HP, New York Times, Citrix, VMWare, Salesforce.

## **University of Michigan Library** · Application Programmer

Ann Arbor, MI

SEP 2007 - MAR 2008

- Facilitated exposure of library resources by implementing del.icio.us-like tagging architecture using CakePHP. Developed an API for external sites to access tagging data allowing integrations with other library databases.
- Oversaw redesign and maintenance for the university's 19 library web sites.

<sup>&</sup>lt;sup>2</sup> See major Google launches & projects

### **EDUCATION**

## **University of Michigan**

SEPT '02 - JUNE '07

BSE Computer Engineering, BSE Electrical Engineering, Cum Laude

### **SKILLS**

**Web Technologies:** Vanilla JavaScript, ES5 - ESNext, TypeScript, React, Node, HTML, CSS, web components, Polymer, AngularJS, Rails

**Tools / Software**: NextJS, Rollup, Webpack, Babel, Browserify, ESLint, Prettier, Gulp, Mocha, RTL/Enzyme, NPM/Yarn, Sass, Chrome Developer Tools, Lighthouse, headless Chrome & Puppeteer, Docker, VS Code, Git, Jira, Mode, Matlab, Keynote, Photoshop, Figma, Sketch

Languages: JS, TypeScript, Python, PHP, Ruby, C++

Platforms & OS: AWS, GCP, Firebase, macOS, Linux, Windows, Chrome OS, Android

### **TALKS / PUBLICATIONS**

- "Using the HTML5 Filesystem API" (2011) O'Reilly Media, Google Press
- Authored 100+ technical articles for web.dev, html5rocks.com, developers.google.com
- Respected <u>speaker</u> at large events (Google I/O, Chrome Dev Summit, O'Reilly Fluent Conf, JS Conf Asia) generating millions of views

Ann Arbor, MI

### [1] LYFT LAUNCHES

- Delivered Concierge Flex V2 and Assisted Rides (door to door service) for Lyft Business. My involvement ensured the org kept \$20M contract with partners and reduced no-shows by 70% and ~40% fewer support calls.
- Designed and launched Web Fingerprinting service in collaboration with Integrity team, protecting
  Lyft web products from fraud. Annual loss savings of \$7.2M. Rewrote 42 screens for
  account.lyft.com flows which modernized tech stack, adopted design system, and improved first
  render web performance.
- Launched <u>Call A Lyft Ride</u> allowing underserved users to request rides via phone call for the first time. Built Twilio/Flex interactive call center and agent dispatching frontend, SSO, observability pipeline. coverage on CNN, Verge). Improved profit ROI from -34% to +150% in 6mo, now producing \$6 pmm/ride (Lyft avg \$1-2).
- Launched <u>Lyft Rentals</u> for Web in 4 weeks. Mentored two junior eng, re-scoped project, and implemented core booking flow to ensure aggressive deadline. Generates \$300k/yr.

### [2] GOOGLE LAUNCHES

- Launched web.dev led UI design, Lighthouse API & backend data fetch pipeline, user profiles.
- Core contributor on <u>Lighthouse</u> (open source web performance/auditing tool integrated directly
  into the Chrome Developer Tools). Developed 12 core audits, Dockerized CI system with Github,
  online report viewer/<u>sharing</u>, headless Chrome-based <u>Performance Runner</u> to aggregate Google's
  performance recommendations across <u>Lighthouse</u>, WebPageTest, and PageSpeed Insights tools.
- Launched <u>Puppeteer</u> and headless Chrome. Added screencast feature to core library, authored <u>defacto</u> developer <u>docs</u>, created 30 <u>demos</u> for common automation use cases. Built <u>Try Puppeteer</u> online code playground (Node, Docker, App Engine) for devs to easily learn/adot API.
- Launched <u>Google Santa Tracker</u>. Led rewrite modularizing of legacy codebase using <u>Polymer</u>.
   Developed and open sourced first i18n solution for web components, allowing 32M users to enjoy the holiday season every year.
- Launched <u>Google I/O Progressive Web App</u> (2015-16) used by 4.4M developers. Lead developer
  for the official website of Google's largest yearly event. Managed internal stakeholders and
  collaboration with external design agency. Showcased new web technologies for the first time on
  google.com (service worker, push notifications, web components). <u>Open sourced</u> for developers to
  learn from.
- Developed and <u>open sourced</u> interactive <u>UI</u> used for all <u>codelabs</u> across Google's Developer Platform used by 5M developers. Infrastructure was adopted by other industry players (IBM).
- Conceived and led <u>Google Web Components</u>, effort to componentize Google services and APIs by building drop-in, reusable web components. Fostered contributions across 12+ product teams.
- Launched <u>Chrome Feature Dashboard</u> used by hundreds of Blink engineers as part of Chrome's
  official process to launch and communicate new features. The <u>usage metrics</u> allow product teams
  to make better informed decisions on API deprecations. My work inspired similar dashboards from
  Microsoft, Apple, and Mozilla.
- Led <u>developers.chrome.com</u>. Site aligned Chrome's product and developer sites, aggregating docs for extensions, devtools, apps, and mobile.
- Helped shape the design & branding of the original <u>HTML5 Logo</u> and built the <u>badge customizer</u> for developers to include the logos on their site.
- Launched Google Flu Shot Finder on maps.google.com. Built App Engine backend, 3rd party embeddable iframe API, bulk data import, form CMS, and JSON API for nation pharmacies to upload vaccination info. Featured on ABC, MSNBC, flu.gov.
- Co-authored Twitter's TweetDeck demo as part of a <u>keynote demo for 2010 Google I/O</u> to highlight HTML5 features. Twitter used the codebase for many years as the foundation for TweetDeck.